Hey everyone, and thanks for jumping
back into the macroverse.
Today we're going to talk about the US
dollar and why I think the DXY is
actually going to go higher in the short
term, which I think is far from the
consensus view. If you guys like the
content, make sure you subscribe to the
channel, give the video a thumbs up, and
also check out the sale on into the
cryptoverse premium at into the
cryptoverse.com.
As I mentioned previously, ticket prices
for the first ITC conference, Investing
Through the Cycles Conference will be
going up on September 1st. Make sure you
guys get your ticket before then. Let's
go ahead and jump in. So, I have
articulated my views about the dollar
fairly consistently throughout the
years. Forex is is notoriously a
difficult asset class to get correct,
but I want to provide the reasons for
why I think the dollar is actually going
to go higher in the short term rather
than lower, which is the general
consensus view. Now, before we get into
all that, remember over a long period of
time, the purchasing power of basically
all fiat currencies is going as to zero.
Okay. So I expect that the dollar will
be worth less in a few years than it is
today. One of the reasons or because of
that I spent a lot of time talking about
investing because if you don't invest
then you typically just get left behind
because inflation you know just eats up
your your cash alive right the purching
power of what you have goes down. But we
have to remember that the dollar, the
DXY is not a measure of the strength of
the US dollar against say gold or
Bitcoin or the stock market. It's a
measure of the relative strength of the
dollar to other fiat currencies. So you
can believe that the purchasing power of
the US dollar will erode over the long
haul, but still believe over certain
time frames it can actually go up
against other fiat currencies. So that's
probably the most um likely criticism
that you will see. But despite the fact
that we all basically know that the
purchasing power of the dollar will
erode over a long enough period of time,
that doesn't stop it from occasionally
going up, right? and it does that and I
I think it's actually going to get a
fairly substantial move up really soon.
Okay, now let's go through some of the
reasons why.
First of all, we put out I put out what
I thought the dollar was going to do in
late 2024. I believe we made a video on
it. I also posted about it on Twitter
where I sort of drew out what I thought
was going to happen where basically the
idea was that the dollar would go up to
about 110. I talk about it over here. Go
up to about 110. Um
I think I even said it go but basically
the idea is that it would go up and then
starting in 2025 we would see the dollar
collapse down to new cycle lows. So you
can see that right go up. Do not print a
new high. In fact, basically come up
where this prior peak is right there in
in sort of like the middle of 2022, but
not to take out the high, but to
actually go down and take out the low.
And when you look at what the dollar
actually did back then, you can see that
it went all the way up, swept the high
from about mid 2022, and then sold off
to new lows. So this has played out so
far. Now, you might say, well, where did
this come from, right? I assure you I do
not have a crystal ball. I do not
because I do get plenty of things wrong.
But one of the places this came from was
assuming that history would more or less
repeat itself. And in fact, it did. And
you can actually see this very clearly.
If you go over to on on the Into the
Cryptoverse website, we actually have an
area where it says politics. Now, I
don't talk about politics a lot, but we
do have some charts that track how
assets perform under different
administrations. And one of the charts
that we have that I actually spent a lot
of time looking at is called
presidential term return paths. And if
you go up here to the asset selector,
you can actually change this to a lot of
different assets and look at how that
asset did under various administrations
going all the way back to the 1950s. But
what we're going to do is we're going to
look to see how the dollar performed
under Trump's first term compared to his
second term. So when I was thinking
about how will the dollar play out back
when I made that, you know, that video
back in like late 2024 and I I tweeted
about it, the idea was that it would
basically follow what it did going into
Trump's first term. And going into
Trump's first term, if you go all the
way back to when he was elected back in
2016 and then he took office um in
January of uh 2017, what you'll notice
is that the dollar spiked up and then
inauguration day was, you know, like
somewhere around here and then a it
spiked up into the inauguration and then
dropped after the inauguration. But what
you'll notice is that it it topped in
January of 2017 and then it bottomed in
February of 2018. Okay, so that's what
the dollar did back then. It topped in
January and then dropped back down into
February and then it carved out a low,
right? It carved out a low and then
started trending back up. You see that?
Now, look, when I made this post back
then, the idea was that we would go up
into early 2025 and then sell off
throughout uh throughout the rest of
2025. And the the idea was that we would
just basically repeat what happened back
in the first cycle. And in fact, if you
were to look I'm not a big believer on
just like looking at fractals or
anything like that, but if you were just
to look at like a bar pattern of the
dollar go, you know, for going into
Trump's first term versus second term,
there's a lot of similarities there,
right? like it spiked up into the
inauguration and then it sold off and
then it carved out a low and then it
begrudgingly started to go higher
probably despite many administ you know
many politicians desire for it to
actually go lower because a lot of times
when the dollar is going up it actually
can act as a headwind for risk assets.
For instance, if you were to look at the
dollar and color code it with the risk
of Bitcoin when the dollar is going up
the risk on Bitcoin that that I have for
the website is normally going down.
It's, you know, the dollar going up is
is oftentimes a headwind for Bitcoin and
that's why the Bitcoin price can often
go down during that period. And you'll
see that the dollar was going up in
2014. It was going up, you know, over
here in 2022, but also it was
begrudgingly going higher in 2018 as
well, which is what I think is happening
right now, right? Like it's begrudgingly
going higher in 2026. I was actually on
on a stage uh at one of the Bitcoin
conferences, not it was not actually the
the a stage for the Bitcoin conference.
was this other organization I was
talking about and I talked about how the
dollar would likely go up in in 2026 and
that it would likely carve out a low and
it was not necessarily you know the
consensus view but and I know right now
like it it feels like the dollar is
going down but it's actually trending up
right I mean you can see there's a
series now of higher lows potentially
here but also higher highs so to me the
trend is already there for anyone
willing to kind acknowledge it. But
obviously if you have sort of like a you
know maybe you have a different view but
I also I also want to talk about like
where this is coming from. Okay. So
obviously you have the presidential term
path. You can see that the dollar sold
off during Trump's second term just like
it did during the first term in the
first year and then for the first half
of 20 of the midterm year it kind of
carves out a low and then starts going
higher. I think that the dollar, just
like we got at the at the end of of 2017
or sorry, the end of 2018, I think the
dollar is going to get a big bounce
going into the end of the year. So, I
think that's kind of how it's going to
play out. I think that it's likely going
to provide one final headwind for
Bitcoin, perhaps one final headwind for
the stock market to get that correction
that the stock market normally gets
starting at about August or September.
Probably, you know, I could easily see
it waiting until September to start,
perhaps around the next Fed meeting. But
that is is what I think is going to
happen. Okay, I think the dollar is
actually going to go higher from here.
And I could see it leaving people kind
of puzzled as to why. But one really
interesting chart to take into account
is if you plot the dollar with the
2-year yield, you can see that they more
or less line up, right? Like if the
2-year yield is going up, the dollar can
often start to spike around those times.
If the 2-year yield is collapsing, then
the dollar can often collapse. You'll
see that in 2021, you'll see that the
dollar was going up, and so too was the
2-year yield. Recently, though, you
could argue that the 2-year yield has
actually gotten a bigger bounce off of
the lows than the dollar has. And I
think that the dollar is going to follow
this. One of the reasons for this is
because I think we're likely going to
have to get another rate hike. I put out
a video yesterday saying that I believe
the rate cutting cycle is already over.
There's a lot of people that would
disagree with that and that's fine. I
mean, that's what makes it a market is
that we, you know, we're going to
disagree. But when you look at at
interest rates internationally and not
just in the United States, one of the
things you'll notice is that in the Euro
area, Japan, the UK, and China, as well
as I believe like New Zealand, maybe not
the UK yet, but a lot of these places
have they've already started raising
rates, right? Like some of them have
already started. And so the idea that
you know the rate hiking cycle is maybe
the uh one of these has not, China has
not, right? But the idea that the rate
hiking cycle is starting is actually
clear when you look at some of the
countries, right? Like Europe has
already started, Japan has started, New
Zealand has started, uh there's a few
others that I believe has started in
here. I Australia has started. I think
it's only a matter of time before the
United States has to start as well. Now,
that might seem weird, but there's
actually some precedent for that. Okay,
so let's go look at what that precedent
is. If you were to go look at the dollar
in the 90s, one of the things you'll
notice about the dollar in the 90s is
that it was actually going up for a lot
of it. Okay? You can see that. But you
might notice that when the Fed first
started to really raise rates in the
mid90s, you see that the dollar actually
went down
for a lot of that. it it's not lined up
perfectly I don't think but the dollar
maybe it is but the dollar basically
went down while the Fed was raising
rates but then when the Fed started to
lower rates dollar started to go up and
when the Fed did raise rates by only 25
basis points the dollar had a big move
up you see that the dollar had an
actually really really big move up when
the the Fed just simply raised 25 basis
points in fact the dollar went from
around 85 all the way up to 90 96 or so
around that increase in in the Fed funds
rate and it didn't mean the market cycle
was over. It didn't mean the business
cycle was over but it did lead to a very
brief correction in the stock market. So
there's a case to be had here that what
if the Fed does something similar? What
if they just simply raised 25 basis
points and then just let it sit for a
while?
That's what they did in the '90s. And if
you look at the expectation
for the Fed, if you look at um you know
the the Fed watch tool here, let's
reload it just to make sure we have the
most recent data. What you'll notice is
that the market is currently thinking
there's going to be a rate hike before
the end of the year. But then if there
is one, the Fed, the market thinks the
Fed is just going to stay at 4%.
Basically, I mean, you can see this all
the way through 2027. Now, this this
probability chart has been wrong plenty
of times in the past, but I'm just
showing you that there's actually a very
plausible outcome towards a rate hike
and subsequently if there is a rate
hike, likely a big move up by the
dollar. So, what I could see happening
is the dollar, you know, maybe coming
back down or coming back up to to these
levels back over here, perhaps up to
like 105, 106, something like that. And
then maybe once we get out into like the
the election year, perhaps selling back
off again like it did in 2020, but not
because of the pandemic, perhaps because
of of some other reason. But I I really
think that there's a lot of validity
here to the dollar actually going higher
rather than lower. And again, that's
going to run against consensus, I
believe. But I actually think it is the
most likely outcome. And the reason why
I think the Fed will likely have to
raise rates is because I I don't think
inflation is necessarily tackled yet.
We've already seen energy prices start
to go back up. If you guys follow my
macro views on on the stock market and
energy and the last two major business
cycles, we saw uh energy top out well
after the stock market did. Like the
stock market topped in March of 2000.
XLE didn't top until May of 2001. The
stock market also topped in October of
2007. XLE didn't top until May of 2008.
So there's already precedent for energy
prices rem and energy stocks going up
even after the stock market tops. And
the fact that the stock market keeps
putting in new highs makes me think that
energy prices are only going to go
higher. I've been adamant that energy
prices will likely be going or the
energy sector will be going back to new
highs before the end of the year. And
now we're there, right? We're already
there. So because of this, because XLE
is putting in new highs, it more or less
confirms the view that I've been saying.
It means to me that the next move for
the Fed will likely be a rate hike and
not a rate cut. And if that's the case,
I think the dollar is going to go
higher. And if that's the case, it means
that final headwind for Bitcoin in the
stock market will likely occur before
the end of the midterm year. And that is
why I think the dollar is going to go
higher. If you guys like the content,
make sure you subscribe to the channel,
give the video a thumbs up, and again,
check out the sale on Into the
Cryptoverse Premium at into the
cryptoverse.com. If you would like to
talk about riveting topics such as this,
but you want to do it in person, check
out the ITC conference coming to you. uh
in Miami in late November. Ticket prices
are going up on September 1st. And if
you want to read more about these views
that I've expressed, I published a
fairly lengthy report yesterday called
the balance of risks. If you just go to
the ITC uh or if you go to the
benjamanc.com
website, you can just click on reports
and then you can just click on the
balance of risks, you can put your email
in and get it completely for free. Or
you can just scroll down to the bottom
of the page and read it directly on the
website if you would prefer to do so.
But those are my views. I think the
dollar will in fact go higher. I think
it's going to come as you get that rate
hike and and the dollar might start
going up before the rate hike. And the
rate hike is likely going to happen
because we realize that inflation is not
actually tackled just yet. Thank you
guys for tuning in. Subscribe and I'll
see you next time. Bye.